RG 052, Civil War Centennial Commission
Connecticut State Library
Civil War Centennial Commission records
1959-1965
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Civil War Centennial Commission
4 cubic feet
In 1959, the General Assembly created the Civil War Centennial Commission to promote and publicize the history of Connecticut’s participation in the Civil War. The Commission consisted of twenty-five appointed members and had an office in the State Library.
RG052
T002712
Historical Note
In 1959, the General Assembly created the Civil War Centennial Commission to promote and publicize the history of Connecticut’s participation in the Civil War. The Commission consisted of twenty-five appointed members, with Albert D. Putnam as Chairman, and had an office in the State Library. It held about twenty meetings between November 1959 and March 1965. It encouraged the formation of local groups to organize pageants, celebrations, and commemorative events, provided speakers, promoted publication of pamphlets about Civil War leaders from Connecticut, and distributed publications. John Niven wrote his book,
Connecticut for the Union; the Role of the State in the Civil War
, for the Commission. By the end of June 1965, the Commission had ended its work, and members' appointments expired on December 15, 1965.
Scope and Content
The record group contains administrative files, minutes of meetings, general correspondence, correspondence with towns and other states, newsletters, drafts of unpublished works, publications and related materials of the Commission, and publications from other state Centennial organizations.
Related Material
RG 005:034, John Dempsey gubernatorial records, Box A-237, Civil War Centennial Commission, 1958-1965.
RG 113, Grand Army of the Republic, Connecticut Department, 1929-1935.
The Manuscript Collections contain many items pertaining to the participation of Connecticut residents in the Civil War.
John Niven, Connecticut for the Union; the Role of the State in the Civil War, (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1965 )
[CSL call number: E499.N5].
The Newsletter published by the Commission (4 issues, 1961-1962) [CSL call number: C489/n].
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Civil War Centennial Commission
Persons:
Putnam, Albert D.
Subjects:
Connecticut. Civil War Centennial Commission -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Centennial celebrations, etc
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Pamphlets; Newsletters; Reports; Membership lists; Financial records
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1959-1965
  - 1. Report, 1965 August (Box 1)
    Copy and draft of the Commission's final report to the Governor.
  - 2. Minutes of meetings, 1959 November 12-1965 March 5 (Box 1)
  - 3. Lists of members (Box 1)
  - 4. General correspondence, 1959-1965
    Roughly chronological.
    - 1959-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - 5. Correspondence with towns, 1959-1965 (Box 2)
    Alphabetical by town. Separate folder for towns with "No Committee".
  - 6. Correspondence with other states, 1959-1965 (Box 2)
  - 7. Correspondence, releases, working materials, 1959-1965 (Box 3)
    Largely unfiled papers pertaining to the work of the Commission. Includes newsletters, drafts of unpublished articles, Civil War music, etc.
    Some grouped by subject.
  - 8. Publications and related materials, 1959-1965 (Box 4-5)
    Contains copies of Commission publications, as listed below, with drafts, correspondence with printers, authors and publishers, requests for copies, etc. Includes correspondence related to John Niven's Connecticut for the Union; the Role of the State in the Civil War.
    - The Connecticut Civil War Centennial - a manual for its observance in the towns and cities of the state of Connecticut, 1960, 31 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Suggestions for 1963 Memorial Day Celebrations, William E. Mills, Jr. (Box 4-5)
    - The Connecticut Civil War Centennial - Connecticut military and naval leaders in the Civil War, E.P. Leddy and Edward J. Lonergan, 43 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Major General John Sedgwick, U.S. Volunteers (1813-64), Robert J. Jurgen and Allen Keller, 31 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Major General Joseph R. Hawley, Soldier and Editor (1826-1905), Albert D. Putnam, 1964 June, 84 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Major General Alfred Howe Terry (1827-1890) Hero of Fort Fisher, William J. Finan, 52 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - So the War Came, Peter B. Schroeder. (Box 4-5)
    - Connecticut Physicians in the Civil War, Stanley B. Weld, 61 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Andrew Hull Foote, Gunboat Commodore (1806-1863), Allen Keller, 48 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - Lincoln in Hartford, J. Doyle De Witt, 15 pages. (Box 4-5)
    - The Civil War, James I. Robertson, Jr., 1963, 63 pages. (Box 4-5)
  - 9. Administrative files, 1959-1965 (Box 6-7)
    Contains budget, statements, purchase orders, requisitions, travel authorizations, invoices, payment lists, vendors' correspondence ("Merchandise") and related papers.
    Unarranged.
  - 10. Publications of other states, 1959-1965 (Box 7-8)
    Contains copies of pamphlets and other materials published by Civil War Centennial organizations in other states and by private or non-governmental agencies.